[Music]
consider a triangle with sides of length
a
b
and c
and angle theta opposite to c
draw the circle containing the triangle
using the side length of a as the radius
extend the radius to a full diameter
and extend the side length c to a
diameter by connecting a radius of
length a and a segment of length a minus
c
extending the side length b to the
circle
and connecting that line to the other
end of the horizontal diameter
results in a right triangle according to
thaley's triangle theorem
this right triangle has a hypotenuse of
length 2 times a
this means that the leg adjacent to the
angle theta has length 2a cosine of
theta
therefore the line segment extending the
length
b to the circle has length two a cosine
theta minus b
now we have two intersecting chords in
the circle
[Music]
so by the intersecting chords theorem
we get that the product of two a cosine
theta minus b
times b
equals
the product a minus c
times
a plus c
expanding both products produces the
equality
2 a times b cosine theta minus b squared
equals a squared minus c squared
adding b squared plus c squared to both
sides results in two a times b cosine
theta plus c squared equals a squared
plus b squared
this is the law of cosines
[Music]
you